Serge Keleher Papers, Inclusive: 1945—1995, undated, Bulk:1988-1989
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Serge Keleher Papers
Inclusive: 1945—1995, undated, Bulk:1988-1989
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
19
Keleher, Serge, 1942 - 2011
2 A4 document boxes
The Serge Keleher Papers contain materials produced or collected by Fr. Serge Keleher, a Catholic priest and Keston staff researcher specializing in the Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Brian Eugene Regis Keleher (Ó Céileachair) was born on June 7, 1942, in New York City to Irish American parents James and Dorothy Keleher. His Roman Catholic baptism is registered at St. Michael’s Roman Catholic Church in mid-town Manhattan. He joined the Eastern Orthodox Church in February 1961, studied in St. Vladimir’s Orthodox Theological Seminary, and was ordained subdeacon in October 1964 by Bishop Dositheus (Mikhail Matveyevich Ivanchenko) in St. Demetrius Church in Jackson, Michigan. In 1966, he earned a B.A. in Political Science and Religious Studies from Michigan State University. Just over a year later, Bishop Dositheus ordained him as a priest in St. Nicholas Cathedral in New York City. Keleher took the name Serge. Shortly thereafter, the Church appointed him as Pastor of Holy Trinity Church in Baltimore, Maryland, where he served until 1970.
In 1970, Archbishop Joseph Raya (Archbishop of Galilee, Palestine) reconciled him back to the Catholic Church, assigning him to the Ukrainian Catholic Eparchy of Toronto, Canada. From 1971-1974, he served several churches and missions in Ontario and rose to the rank of Archpriest in 1978. In 1980, he completed theological studies at the University of St. Michael’s College, University of Toronto, where he received an M.A. in Sacred Theology. Trips to Ukraine began in 1981, and in 1988, Keleher was named Mitrophoric Archimandrite. In the 1980’s, he worked as the private secretary to Bishop Isidore Borecky of Toronto and accompanied the Bishop to Ukraine, Poland, and Hungary in 1989.
Fr. Serge moved to Dublin, Ireland, and occasionally served as a staff researcher specializing in the Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church for Keston College in Oxford. While at Keston, he published Passion and Resurrection: The Greek Catholic Church in Soviet Ukraine, 1939-1989 (Lviv: Stauropegion, 1993). That year, Fr. Serge Keleher translated Cyril Korolevsky’s biography of Metropolitan Andrew Sheptytsky from the original French. His scholarly interests during the 1990s focused on new opportunities for Catholic-Orthodox dialogue which his continued research and travels to Ukraine further informed. His “Orthodox Rivalry in the Twentieth Century: Moscow Versus Constantinople” in Religion, State & Society vol. 25, no.2 (1997) surveyed the historical conflicts between the Byzantine, Russian and other autocephalous Orthodox churches. During the 1990s and into the 21st century, he also served as spiritual father to the Ukrainian Greek Catholic community in Dublin where he died on November 11, 2011.
Scope and Content
The Serge Keleher Papers cover the period from 1945 to 1995 with the bulk in 1989. They focus on the liturgy, condition, and organization of the Ukrainian Catholic (Uniate) Church as well as dialogue between Catholicism and Orthodoxy. This collection contains documents predominately from the Ukrainian Catholic Church in Canada.
Arrangement
The Serge Keleher papers were filed together with other documents related to the Ukrainian Catholic (Uniate) Church. They have been described and filed separately to indicate the generation of ideas and activities by Serge Keleher.
The Serge Keleher papers are organized into six series: I. Subject Files, II. Collected Works, III. Correspondence, IV. Personal Documents, V. Literary Productions, and VI. Printed Materials
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 19.
Related Resources
Related references
Religious Information Service of Ukraine. “Serge Keleher: Larger than Life,” Religious Information Service of Ukraine. Last updated January 31, 2013.
Serge Keleher, “Orthodox Rivalry in the Twentieth Century: Moscow Versus Constantinople,” Religion, State & Society vol. 25, no. 2 (1997): 125-137.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Borets)'kyiămp;&, Izydor, -- 1911-; Dat︠s︡enko, Ivan, (Ivan Ivanovich), 1918.; Keleher, Serge.; Korolevsky, Cyril, 1878-1959.; Myroslav Ivan, Major Archbishop of Ukrainian Catholics,1914-2000.; Sheptyt︠s︡)'kyĭ, Andriĭ, hraf, 1865-1944.; Slipyi, Iosyf, 1892-1984.
Subjects (Organizations)
Catholic Church -- Byzantine rite, Ukrainian.; Catholic Church -- Relations -- Orthodox Eastern Church.; Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.; Orthodox Eastern Church -- Relations -- Catholic Church.; Ukrainian Catholic Church in Canada.
Places
Soviet Union -- Church history.; Ukraine -- Church history -- 20th century.
Genres
Brochures.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Newsletters.; Records (Documents)
- Subject Files, 1945-1994; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Subject Files series contains newspaper and journal clippings, correspondence, hand written notes, and manuscripts covering theology, millennium celebration, church administration, Catholic-Orthodox dialog, and conversion to Orthodoxy.
  - Our Lady's Shrine, Knock, Co Mayo, Ireland, 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bishop Isidore Borecky Resignation, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bishop Isidore Borecky, 1988 May-July (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1988 Translation of Divine Liturgy of St. John Crysostom to Ukrainian, 1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Autocephalous Ukrainian Catholic Church, 1990, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Catholic-Orthodox Dialog, 1992-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Group Conversion to Orthodoxy, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Collected Materials, 1945-1993; 2
  The Collected Materials series contains published articles, liturgical texts, documents, and reports by various authors.
  - Article by Cyril Korolevskij "Liturgical Publications of the Congregation for the Eastern Church, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Proclamation of the Word "Orthodox" at Divine Services, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Article by Richard Toporoski "The Language of Worship", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Message of the Supreme Pontiff John Paul II to the Ukrainian Catholics on the Occasion of the Millennium of the Baptism of Kievan Rus', 1988 February 14 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Metropolitan Volodymyr (Sterniuk). Sermons and Pastoral Letters, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fr. Iwan Dacko, "988-1988 The Ukrainian Catholics in the Millennium of Their Baptism", 1989 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cardinal Myroslav Lubachivsky's Address at Keston College, 1989 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Report on Trip to the Soviet Union on 17-31 July 1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Message of His Holiness Pope John Paul II for the Celebration of the World Day, 1990 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hryniewicz, Waclaw. Articles, 1992, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Liturgical Texts: Service to Blessed John, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, 1967-1995; 3
  The Correspondence series contains personal correspondence between the Vatican, Keston, and Orthodox and Ukrainian Catholic Church leaders from the diaspora.
  - Correspondence (1 of 4), 1970-1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence (2 of 4), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence (3 of 4), 1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence (4 of 4), 1994 October-1995 January (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence. Bishop Isidore Borecky Resignation, 1989 April-May (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence. Bishop Isidore Borecky Travel to Hungary, Poland, and Ukraine, 1989 June-October (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Personal Documents, 1994-1995; 4
  The Personal documents series consists of certificates of elevation to the rank of Archbishop, letters of appointments and promotions, legal documents, and financial statements from the period when Fr. Serge Keleher lived in Oxford, United Kingdom.
  - Certificates and Letters of Appointments and Promotions, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Property Rental Agreement, 1994 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Tax Bills, 1994 October-1995 March (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Literary Productions, 1989-1994; 5
  The Literary Production series contains copies of published articles, travel reports, and draft manuscripts.
  - Untitled Article on World Council of Churches' Attitude on Irish Struggle, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Conference Paper of Ukrainian Church Iconography in Canada, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Summary and Translation of Fr. Kostel'nyk's 1946 Address to the Assembly, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Translation of Cardinal Casaroli's Memorandum of the Holy See to Gorbachev, 1988 June 13 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Romanian Greek-Catholic Church. Article in Religion, State and Society, Vol. 22, No. 4, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Two Visits to Eastern Europe by Bishop Isidore of Toronto and Eastern Canada, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1946 L'viv Church Council, 1989 January 9 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Pelvetsky and Melnyk - Bishops of What Church?, 1989 January 12 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Proposal for Assistance to the Greek Catholics in Transcarpathian Region of the USSR, 1989 March 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Printed Materials, 1994; 6
  The Printed Materials series contains Catholic, Ukrainian Catholic, and Orthodox publications from the Vatican, Canada, the United States, Russia, and Ukraine.
  - Information Sheet of the Holy Protection Ukrainian Catholic Church in Thunder Bay, Canada, 1972 September 3 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - An Inaugural Lecture "The Origin of Rus'", Harvard University, Massachusetts, 1975 October 24 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ukrainian Serials. Research Report No. 3, University of Alberta, Edmonton, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Publication of University of Toronto (Canada) Andrei Sheptyts'kyi Conference, 1984 November 22-24 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Ukrainian Orthodox Calendar, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Issues of the Ukrainian Canadian, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Millennium of Christianity in Ukraine Issue of Australian-Ukrainian Review, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Apostolic Letter of the Supreme Pontiff John Paul II to the Episcopate of the Catholic Church on the Occasion of the 1200th Anniversary of the Second Council of NICAEA, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Briefing Vol. 18, No. 18, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Tserkovnyi Visnyk, 1989 May 14 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Booklet Published for Bishop Isidore Borecky's Triple Jubilee, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Service Orthodoxe de Presse, 1990 August-October (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Information Bulletin of All-Ukrainian Fraternity of St Andriw Pervozvannyof the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of Kievan Patriarchate, 1994 July (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Issues of L'Osservatore Romano, 1994 August-November (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Church Calendar and Typicon, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Announcement of Republication of the Liturgicon, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Christmas Flyer of the Monastery of the Holy Transfiguration, CA, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Russia Travel Guide, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Ural'skii Sledopyt, No. 6, 1992 May (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Advertisement Flyers, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Image of Lifegiving Cross by Juvenalij Mokryckyj, Studite, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)